So, the topic today is dynamic programming.
我们今天来讲动态规划
The term programming in the name of this term
本质上来说  这里的“编程”
doesn't refer to computer programming.
并不是指实际的计算机编程
OK, programming is an old word that means
其实  编程这个名词的本义是
any tabular method for accomplishing something.
按照一定的步骤来解决问题
So, you'll hear about linear programming
你们可能已经听说过线性规划
and dynamic programming.
和动态规划
Either of those, even though we now incorporate
无论哪个  尽管我们现在在编程中
those algorithms in computer programs,
使用这些算法
originally computer programming,
但在实际计算机编程时
you were given a datasheet and you put
你要做的是写出一行一行的
one line per line of code as a tabular method
能够按步骤执行的代码
for giving the machine instructions as to what to do.
这样电脑才会明白如何执行这项工作
OK, so the term programming is older.
这里说的“编程”是以前的表达方式了
Of course, and now conventionally when you see programming
当然  按照惯例我们说编程的时候
you mean software, computer programming.
指的都是电脑程序的编程
But that wasn't always the case.
哦  严格来说倒也不一定
And these terms continue in the literature.
文献上说的编程还是讲它的本义
So, dynamic programming is a design technique like other
动态规划就是一种设计的技巧
design techniques we've seen such as divided and conquer.
就像我们以前讲过的分而治之法
OK, so it's a way of solving a class of problems
也就是说它是解决一类问题的方法
rather than a particular algorithm or something.
而不是某种固定的算法
So, we're going to work through this for the example of
我们通过一个具体的例子来学习这种方法
so-called longest common subsequence problem
就是传说中的最长公共子序列问题
sometimes called LCS, OK,
缩写是LCS【译注：后面会用LCS来代替最长公共子序列】
which is a problem that comes up in a variety of contexts.
这个问题在很多地方都会出现
And it's particularly important in computational biology
在计算生物学里尤为重要
where you have long DNA strains and you're trying to
比如你想在一些DNA长链里
find commonalities between two strings
找到两条链里相同的部分
OK, one which may be a genome and one may be various
比如其中一段序列是基因组序列
when people do, what is that thing called
它们是用什么东西
when they do the evolutionary comparisons?
来表示演化过程的比较的？
The evolutionary trees, yeah, right, yeah, exactly,
演化树  对  更准确一点的说法？
phylogenetic trees, there you go, OK, phylogenetic trees.
系统发生树  很给力嘛  对  就是系统发生树
Good, so here's the problem.
很好  下面说一下这个问题
So, you're given two sequences, x going from one to m
给定两个序列  x是从1到m
and y running from one to n
y从1到n
You want to find a longest sequence common to both.
然后找出它们的LCS
OK, and here I say a, not the, although it's common to
这里要提一下  尽管在一般情况下
talk about the longest common subsequence.
我们称之为最长公共子序列
Usually the longest common subsequence isn't unique.
但通常 最长公共子序列并不唯一
There could be several different subsequences
可能有很多子序列
that tie for that.
都是最长公共子序列
However, people tend to, it's one of the sloppinesses
不过通常情况下
that people will say.
大家都说的不太严谨
I will try to say a, unless it's unique.
我习惯说“之一”  除非最长公共子序列的确只有一个
But I may slip as well because
不过我也有可能说走嘴
it's just such a common thing to just talk about the,
因为大家平时都这么说
even though there might be multiple.
忽略了它可能不唯一的情况
So, here's an example.
现在来看例子吧
Suppose x is this sequence, and y is this sequence.
令x是这个序列  y是这个序列
So, what is a longest common subsequence
它们的LCS是什么？
See if you can just eyeball it.
看看你们能不能直接用肉眼看出来
AB, length two?
AB  长度只有2吗？
Anybody have one longer? Excuse me?
谁找到更长的了吗？大声点说出来
BDB, BDB. BDAB, BDAB, BDAB, anything longer?
BDB, BDB. BDAB, BDAB, BDAB, 还有别的吗？
So, BDAB, that's the longest one.
那么BDAB就是那个最长的
Is there another one that's the same length?
有没有哪个是和它同一长度的？
Is there another one that ties?
有没有和它不相上下的？
BCAB, BCAB, another one?
BCAB BCAB 还有一个？
BCBA, yeah, there are a bunch of them all of length four.
BCBA,很好, 这些都是长度为4的
There isn't one of length five.
没有长度是5的公共子序列
OK, we are actually going to come up with an algorithm that,
好  那我们现在就用算法来证明
if it's correct, we're going to show it's correct
我们上面目测的都是正确的
guarantees that there isn't one of length five.
确保真的没有长度为5的公共子序列
So all those are, we can say, any one of these
对于这个几个子序列  我们可以这样说
is the longest common subsequence of x and y.
任意一个都是x和y的LCS
We tend to use it this way using functional notation
这里我们更喜欢用函数符号来表示
but it's not a function that's really a relation.
不过本质上其实是一种关系而非函数
So, we'll say something is an LCS
于是我们就把这个叫做LCS
when really we only mean it's an element
指的是那些LCS里其中的一个
Once again, it's classic abusive notation.
当然  这个表示也不是很标准的
As long as we know what we mean, it's OK to abuse notation.
不过只要我们自己心里清楚  就没什么大问题
What we can't do is misuse it. But abuse, yeah!
当然别乱用符号 不过随意一点也很好嘛！
Make it so it's easy to deal with.
简单点表示更利于表达
But you have to know what's going on underneath.
当然前提是你清楚它的本质是什么
OK, so let's see, so there's a fairly simple
那么我们继续  这个问题可以用
brute force algorithm for solving this problem.
穷举法来解决
And that is, let's just check every, maybe some of
就是要检查每一个——也许你们
you did this in your heads, subsequence of x from one to m
刚才就是这样想的——x里从1到m的每个子序列
to see if it's also a subsequence of y of one to n.
然后看看y里面是不是也有一样的子序列
So, just take every subsequence that you can get here
就是算出这里面所有的子序列
check it to see if it's in there.
然后检查下面有没有
So let's analyze that.
分析一下
So, to check, so if I give you a subsequence of x,
对于检查这个操作  如果已知一个x的子序列
how long does it take you to check whether it is
你需要花费多少时间来确定
in fact, a subsequence of y?
是不是y的子序列
So, I give you something like BCAB.
比如我给定你BCAB这样的序列
How long does it take me to check to see
我需要多长时间来判断
if it's a subsequence of y?
它是否是y的子序列？
Length of y, which is order n. And how do you do it?
就是y的长度  O(n)  你是怎么知道的？
Yeah, you just scan.
是的  就是扫描一遍
So as you hit the first character that matches, great.
如果发现第一个相同的字符
Now, if you will, recursively see whether
那就按x和y的下标开始递归
the suffix of your string matches the suffix of x.
判断x和y里对应的元素是否相同
OK, and so, you are just simply walking down the tree
总而言之  就是顺着捋一遍
to see if it matches.
看看有没有相同的
You're walking down the string to see if it matches.
遍历这个字符串  看看有没有相同的
OK, then the second thing is
第二个问题是
then how many subsequences of x are there?
x有多少个子序列？
Two to the n?
2^n？
x just goes from one to m, two to the m subsequences of x
x是从1到m  也就是说x的子序列有2^m个
OK, two to the m.
嗯  2^m
Two to the m subsequences of x,
x的子序列有2^m个
OK, one way to see that, you say, well,
有一种方法来计算
how many subsequences are there of something there?
某个序列的子序列有多少个
If I consider a bit vector of length m,
考虑一个长度为m的“位向量”
OK, that's one or zero,
每个位上只可能是0或者1
just every position where there's a one, I take out,
如果有一个元素被标记为1
that identifies an element that I'm going to take out.
那就表示这个元素被我放进了子序列里
OK, then that gives me a mapping from each subsequence of x
这样我就可以得到一个映射  每个x的子序列
from each bit vector to a different subsequence of x.
都对应了一个相应的位向量
Now, of course, you could have matching characters there,
当然  有的子序列的字符可能是相同的
but in the worst case, all of the characters are different.
不过在最坏情况下  所有的字符都是不一样的
OK, and so every one of those will be a unique subsequence.
那样每个子序列都是不同的
So, each bit vector of length m corresponds to a subsequence.
所以每个长为m的位向量 都对应了一个子序列
That's a generally good trick to know.
总体的思想就是这样
So, the worst-case running time of this method
于是这个方法在最坏条件下的运行时间
is order n times two to the m, which is,
就是O(n·2^m)  也就是说
since m is in the exponent, is exponential time.
由于m在指数位上  运行时间也就是指数阶的
And there's a technical term that we use
我们可以用一个术语
when something is exponential time.
描述指数阶时间
Slow, good. OK, very good.
龟速  好吧  嗯  挺好
OK, slow, OK, so this is really bad.
对  就叫龟速  这是很糟糕的情况
This is taking a long time to crank out
这样做需要花费相当长的时间
how long the longest common subsequence is
才能算出最长公共子序列的长度
because there's so many subsequences.
因为子序列实在是太多了
OK, so we're going to now go through a process of
那么我们现在需要设计
developing a far more efficient algorithm for this problem.
一种更给力的算法来解决这个问题
OK, and we're actually going to go through several stages.
可以分为几个步骤
The first one is to go through simplification stage.
第一步是进行简化
OK, and what we're going to do is look at simply
我们来分别看看
the length of the longest common sequence of x and y.
x和y的LCS有多长
And then what we'll do is extend the algorithm
我们要做的就是扩展这个算法
to find the longest common subsequence itself.
使之能够找到最长公共子序列
OK, so we're going to look at the length.
我们从序列的长度入手
So, simplify the problem, if you will,
那么先试着简化计算
to just try to compute the length.
LCS长度这个问题
What's nice is the length is unique.
令人愉快的是  这个长度是唯一的
OK, there's only going to be one length
所谓的最大长度
that's going to be the longest.
有且仅有一个
OK, and what we'll do is just focus on
于是我们现在要做的就是
the problem of computing the length.
如何计算LCS的长度
And then we'll do is we can back up from that and figure out
然后我们再回过头来看看
what actually is the subsequence that realizes that length.
哪个公共子区间达到了这个长度
OK, and that will be a big simplification because we don't
这样做就简化了很多
have to keep track of a lot of different possibilities
因为我们无需在意其它的可能性
at every stage. We just have to keep track of
我们要做的就是记录
the one number, which is the length.
一个最大长度的数值
So, it's sort of reduces it to a numerical problem.
这样就把它简化成了一个数值问题
We'll adopt the following notation.
我们会用到这样的符号
It's pretty standard notation, but I just want,
这个符号很常见  不过在这里——
if I put absolute values around the string or a sequence,
如果我对一个序列加了绝对值符号
it denotes the length of the sequence, S.
它表示的是这个序列的长度  S
OK, so that's the first thing. The second thing we're going to
嗯  这是第一点  接下来我们要做的
do is, actually, we're going to,
我们要做的——
which takes a lot more insight when you come up with
对付这样的问题需要你的优化意识
a problem like this, and in some sense,
从某种意义上来说
ends up being the hardest part of designing a good dynamic
要设计一个优秀的动态规划算法
programming algorithm from any problem, which is we're going to
意识才是最重要的
actually look not at all subsequences of x and y,
这样我们就不用考虑x和y的所有子序列了
but just prefixes.
而只是它们的前缀
OK, we're just going to look at prefixes and we're going to
我们要做的只是考量它们的前缀
show how we can express the length of the longest common
以及如何用这些前缀来描述
subsequence of prefixes in terms of each other.
它们自己的LCS长度
In particular, we're going to define c of ij
特别的  我们定义c[i,j]
to be the length, the longest common subsequence
来记录x和y的LCS长度
of the prefix of x going from one to i,
x的前缀是从1到i的
and y of going to one to j.
y的前缀则是从1到j
And what we are going to do is
之后我们要做的就是
we're going to calculate c[i,j] for all ij.
算出这些个c[i,j]
And if we do that, how then do we solve the
如果这个完成了之后  那接下来如何
problem of the longest common of sequence of x and y?
算出x和y的最长公共子序列？
How do we solve the longest common subsequence?
LCS问题要怎么解？
Suppose we've solved this for all i and j.
在我已经解出了c[i,j]的前提下
How then do we compute the length of the longest common
如何计算x和y的LCS长度的？
subsequence of x and y? Yeah, c[m,n],
嗯  c[m,n]
that's all, OK? So then, c[i,j] of m,n
这就是结果对吧？所以  c[m,n]
is just equal to the longest common subsequence of x and y,
就等于x和y的的LCS
because if I go from one to n, I'm done, OK?
因为下标从1到m再从1到n  就都走过一遍了
And so, it's going to turn out that what we want to do is
那么  我们要做的已经明确了
figure out how to express to c[m,n], in general,
就是找到c[m,n]的归纳式  更一般地说
c[i,j], in terms of other c[i,j].
用其它的c[i,j]来表示c[i,j]
So, let's see how we do that.
来一起看看这是怎么算的
OK, so our theorem is going to say that c[i,j] is just --
于是按照这个公式  c[i,j]就等于——
OK, it says that if the i'th character matches the j'th
意思就是如果x的第i个字符
character, then i'th character of x matches the j'th
和y的第j个字符相等
character of y, then c[i,j] of ij is just
那么c[i,j]就等于
c of i minus one, j minus one plus one.
c[i-1,j-1]+1
And if they don't match,
如果它们不相等
then it's either going to be the longer
那c[i,j]就等于c[i,j-1]和c[i-1,j]中
of c[i,j-1] and c[i-1,j] , OK?
比较大的那一个
So that's what we're going to prove.
我们将要证明它
And that's going to give us a way of relating the calculation
这个公式告诉我们  对于给定的c[i,j]
of a given cji to values that are strictly smaller,
它的值是由两个严格小于它的值决定的
OK, that is at least one of the arguments is smaller of the two
这里面肯定有一个是比较小的
arguments. OK, and that's going to give us
这样我们就知道
a way of being able, then, to understand how to calculate c[i,j].
如何理解c[i,j]的计算过程
So, let's prove this theorem.
我们就来证明这个
So, we'll start with a case x equals y of j.
从x[i]=y[j]的情况开始
And so, let's draw a picture here.
我们来画个图
So, we have x here.
这个是x
And here is y.
这个是y
OK, so here's my sequence, x, which I'm sort of drawing as
这个是序列x  就是这个
this elongated box, sequence y
长长的条形框  下面的是序列y
and I'm saying that x[i] and y[j], those are equal.
当x[i]和y[j]相等的时候
OK, so let's see what that means.
来看一下这是什么意思
OK, so let's let z of one to k be, in fact, the longest common
令最长公共子序列z[1..k]
subsequence of x of one to i, y of one to j,
等于LCS(x[1..i], y[1..j])
where c of ij is equal to k. OK, so the longest common
当c[i,j]=k的时候. 这样的话
subsequence of x and y of one to i and y of one to j has some
x[1..i], y[1..j]的最长公共子序列
value. Let's call it k.
就等于这个k值
And so, let's say that we have some sequence which realizes
然后我们假设有一个序列达到了这个长度
that. OK, we'll call it z.
我们称其为z
OK, so then, can somebody tell me what z of k is?
那谁来说说z[k]是什么东西？
What is z of k here?
这里的z[k]是指什么？
Yeah, it's actually equal to x of i, which is also equal to
是的  其实就等于x[i]  同时也等于y[j]
y of j? Why is that?
为什么是这样的？
Why couldn't it be some other value?
为什么不等于别的值？
Yeah, so you got the right idea.
很好  看来你们找到要领了
So, the idea is, suppose that the sequence
其实就是说  如果z这个序列
didn't include this element here at the last element,
不包含最后面的这个元素
the longest common subsequence. OK, so then it includes a
也就是假设LCS里没有这两个字符
bunch of values in here, and a bunch of values in here,
而在这两个序列里的前面的这些字符都是相等的
same values. It doesn't include this or this.
只是不包含后面这两个字符
Well, then I could just tack on this extra character
那么我就可以向这个LCS中添加这个字符
and make it be longer, make it k plus one
使其长度增加  长度变成k+1
because these two match.
因为最后这两个也是相等的
OK, so if the sequence ended bofore
也就是说如果这个LCS还没到x[i]
-- just extend it by tacking on x[i].
那么在上面加个x[i]就可以让它更长了
OK, it would be fairly simple to just tack on x[i].
加个x[i]不费吹灰之力嘛
OK, so if that's the case,
那么接下来
then if I look at z going one up to k minus one,
对于z[1..k-1]这个序列
that's certainly a common
显然它就是
sequence of x of 1 up to, excuse me, of up to i minus
x[1..i-1]和y[1..j-1]的
one. And, y of one up to j minus one.
最长公共子序列
OK, because this is a longest common sequence.
因为我们已经知道了这是一个最长公共子序列
z is a longest common sequence is,
z[1..k]是x[1..i]和y[1..j]
from x of one to i,y of one to j.
最长公共子序列
And, we know what the last character is.
我们已经知道了最后的那个字符是什么
It's just x[i],or equivalently, y[j].
它就是x[i]  也等于y[j]
So therefore, everything except the last
因此  除了最后的那个字符
character must at least be a common sequence of
其它的z一定是
x of one to i minus one, y of one to j minus one.
x[1..i-1]和y[1..j-1]的一个公共序列
Everybody with me? It must be a common sequence.
都跟上了吧？它一定是一个公共序列
OK, now, what you also suspect?
你们还能想到些什么？
What do you also suspect about z of one to k-1?
你们感觉z[1..k-1]还有点什么猫腻？
It's a common sequence of these two. Yeah?
它是这两个的公共序列  对吧？
Yeah, it's a longest common sequence.
很好  它还是最长公共子序列
So that's what we claim, z of one up to k minus one is
我要说的就是这个命题  z[1..k-1]
in fact a longest common subsequence of x of 1 to i-1
其实就是x[1..i-1]和y[1..j-1]的
and y of one to j minus one, OK?
最长公共子序列
So, let's prove that claim.
下面我们来证明这个命题。
So, we'll just have a little diversion to prove the claim.
要证明这个得绕点弯
OK, so suppose that w is a longer common sequence,
假设w是一个更长的公共子序列
that is, that the length, the w, is bigger than k minus one.
这也就是说w的长度要比k-1大
OK, so suppose we have a longer common sequence than
如果存在一个公共子序列的长度
z of one to k minus one.
比z[1..k-1]长
So, it's got to have length
那么这个子序列的长度
that's bigger than k minus one if it's longer.
就要大于k-1
OK, and now what we do is we use a classic argument you're
接下来我们要用到一个很经典的方法
going to see multiple times, not just this week,
你们将不止一次地遇见它  不仅仅是这周
which it will be important for this week,
对于这周的内容它至关重要
but through several lectures
而且后面的课还会提到它
Hence, it's called a cut and paste argument.
总之  它的名字是“剪贴”法
So, the idea is let's take a look at w,
这个方法就是把w拿出来
concatenate it with that last character, z of k.
把那个最后面的字符z[k]连结在后面
So, this is string, concatenation.
把它们接在一起  连结
OK, so that's just my terminology for string
连结就是接上的术语表示
OK, so I take whatever I claimed was
我可以取一个
a longer common subsequence,
更长的公共子序列
and I concatenate z of k to it.
然后把z[k]和它进行连结
OK, so that is certainly a common sequence of
这个连结后的序列一定是
x of one to i , and y of one to j.
x[1..i]和y[1..j]的一个公共子序列
And it has length bigger than k because it's basically,
它的长度一定大于k  因为——
what is its length?
它的长度是多少？
The length of w is bigger than k minus one.
w的长度就已经比k-1大了
I add one character.
在这之上我又加了一个字符
So, this combination here, now, has length bigger that k.
这里我们进行了合并  合并后的序列长度就大于k了
OK, and that's a contradiction, thereby proving the claim.
于是导出了矛盾  假设不成立  原命题得证
So, I'm simply saying, I claim this.
简单来说就是  我假设
Suppose you have a longer one. Well, let me show,
有一个比更长的公共子序列  也就是说
if I had a longer common sequence for the prefixes
如果两个拿掉了末字符的前缀
where we dropped the character from
它们的一个公共子序列
both strings if it was longer there,
已经比k-1大了
but we would have made the whole thing longer.
这样就会使总体的LCS变大
So that can't be.
而这当然是不可能的
So, therefore, this must be a longest common subsequence,OK?
所以这个拼成的序列一定是一个LCS  对吧
Questions? Because you are going to need
有问题没？因为你们需要学会
to be able to do this kind of proof ad nauseam,almost.
这种苦逼的证明方式
So, if there any questions,let them at me, people.
所以如果有任何问题  直接告诉我就好
OK, so now what we have established is that z one
我们现在已经得到了
through k is a longest common subsequence of the two prefixes
z[1..k]是去掉末字符的两个前缀的
when we drop the last character.
最长公共子序列
So, thus, we have c[i,j] of i minus one
这样的话  我们可以算出
one, j minus one is equal to what?
c[i-1,j-1]等于多少？
What's c[i,j] of i minus one, j minus one?
c[i-1,j-1]是多少？
k minus one. thank you.
k-1.很好
Let's move on with the class,
我们来继续吧
OK, which implies that c[i,j] of ij is just equal to
这说明c[i,j]就等于
c of i minus one, j minus one plus one.
c[i-1,j-1]+1
So, it's fairly straightforward if you think about
刚才讲的这些
what's going on there.
都比较直观
It's not always as straightforward in some problems
其它的一些些LCS问题
as it is for longest common subsequence.
可能并没有这么一目了然
The idea is, so I'm not going to go through the other cases.
我们要讲的是——其它情形我就不赘述了
They are similar.
证明过程都差不多
But, in fact, we've hit on one of
其实我们刚才讲的就是
the two hallmarks of dynamic programming.
动态规划的两个特征之一
So, by hallmarks,
特征的意思
I mean when you see this kind of structure in a problem,
就是当你遇到这种结构的问题时
there's a good chance that dynamic programming
十有八九是可以用动态规划
is going to work as a strategy.
来解决的
The dynamic programming hallmark is the following.
下面说的就是动态规划的特征
This is number one.
下面来讲第一条
And that is the property of optimal substructure.
这也是最优子结构的性质
OK, what that says is an optimal solution to a problem,
意思是问题的一个最优解——
and by this, we really mean problem instance.
问题是指实际的问题实例
But it's tedious to keep saying problem instance.
不过一直称为“问题实例”又太文绉绉
A problem is generally, in computer science,
计算机领域中所说的问题
viewed as having an infinite number of instances typically,
实际上是有无数种不同的实例
OK, so sorting is a problem.
比如排序就是一个问题
A sorting instance is a particular input.
一个排序的实例就是一个特别的输入
OK, so we're really talking about problem instances,
所以我们要处理的都是问题实例
but I'm just going to say problem, OK?
不过口头上我就叫它“问题”了
So, when you have an optimal solution to a problem,
那么  如果一个问题的最优解
contains optimal solutions to subproblems.
包含了子问题的最优解
OK, and that's worth drawing a box around
这里应该框起来
because it's so important.
因为实在很重要
OK, so here, for example,
所以  比如说
if z is a longest common subsequence of x and y,
z是x和y的LCS
OK, then any prefix of z is a longest common subsequence
那么任何z的前缀都是某个x的前缀
of a prefix of x, and a prefix of y, OK?
和某个y的前缀的LCS  对吧
So, this is basically what it says.
嗯  就是这个意思
I look at the problem, and I can see that there is
当我拿到这个问题  我发现了
optimal substructure going on.
里面存在最优子结构
OK, in this case, and the idea is that almost always,
在这种结构下你总是能够——
it means that there's a cut and
在上面应用
paste argument you could do to demonstrate that,
剪贴法来做出证明
OK, that if the substructure were not optimal,
证明如果子问题的解不是最优的
then you'd be able to find a better solution to the overall
那么用剪贴法你总能找到
problem using cut and paste.
一个全局最优解
OK, so this theorem, now, gives us a strategy
根据这个定理  我们可以来
for being able to compute longest common subsequence.
计算LCS问题了
Here's the code; oh wait.
这里是代码——稍等
OK, so going to ignore base cases in this,
那就先忽略这里的初始值
And we will return the value of the longest common subsequence.
返回值就是LCS的长度
It's basically just implementing this theorem.
本质上就是应用前面的那个定理
OK, so it's either the longest common subsequence
它有可能就是LCS  如果x[i]和y[j]
if they match.
是相等的
It's the longest common subsequence of one of the
这时它就等于它的一个前缀+1
prefixes where you drop that character  for both strengths
这个前缀是去掉末尾字符之后的LCS
and add one because that's the matching one.
+1是因为去掉的那个字符就是相等的
Or, you drop a character from x,
如果x[i]和y[j]不等  那么在x末尾去掉一个字符
and it's the longest common subsequence of that.
它就等于这个玩意的LCS
Or you drop a character from y,
或者是y末尾去掉一个字符
whichever one of those is longer.
这两个取最大值
That ends up being the longest common subsequence.
得到的那个就是LCS
OK, so what's the worst case for this program?
这个程序的最坏情况是什么？
What's going to happen in the worst case?
最坏情况下会发生什么？
Which of these two clauses is going to cause us more headache?
这两种情况中的哪种更令我不爽？
The second clause: why the second clause?
第二种情况  为什么呢？
Yeah, you're doing two LCS sub-calculations here.
说得对  这里要进行两次LCS子问题的计算
Here, you're only doing one.
而这种情况下你只会计算一次
Not only that, but you get to decrement both indices,
还不止这样  上面那种情况两个下标都减少1
whereas here you've basically got to,
而下面这种情况
you only get to decrement one index,
每次只有一个下标会减少
and you've got to calculate two of them.
然后还得把这两个都算一次
So that's going to generate the tree.
这个过程是一个树
So, and the worst case,
所以最糟的情况就是
x of i is not equal to x of j for all i and j.
对于所有的i,j  x[i]不等于x[j]【译注：此处应为x[i]不等于y[j]】
So, let's draw a recursion tree for this program to sort of
我们来画一个这个程序的递归树
get an understanding as to what is going on to help us.
来理解一下它是如何工作的
And, I'm going to do it with m equals seven,
我给定m=7
and n equals six.
n=6
OK, so we start up the top with
我们从上面开始
my two indices being seven and six.
下标是7,6
And then, in the worst case, we had to execute these.
在最坏情况下  我们要执行的是这些
So, this is going to end up being six, six, and seven,
所以这边是6,6  那边是7,5
five for indices after the first call.
这是第一层递归
And then, this guy is going to split.
然后这边继续分成两支
And he's going to produce five, six here,
这边是5,6
decrement the first index, i.
下标i 减一得到的
And then, if I keep going down here,
这边继续分下去
we're going to get four, six and five, five.
得到4,6和5,5
And these guys keep extending here.
这边也会延伸下去
I get six five, five five, six four, OK?
得到6,5 5,5 6,4
Over here, I'm going to get decrement the first index,
再算这边  第一个下标减一
six five, and I get five five, six four,
6,5 它下面是5,5 6,4
and these guys keep going down. And over here,
一直下去  再到这边
I get seven four. And then we get six four,
得到7,4  然后是6,4
seven three, and those keep going down.
7,3  下面继续分
So, we keep just building this tree out.
好的  我们把这棵树画出来了
OK, so what's the height of this tree?
这个树的高度是多少？
Not of this one for the particular value of m and n,
不是指这个情况下的具体数值
but in terms of m and n.
而是用m和n来表示
What's the height of this tree?
树的高度是多少？
It's the max of m and n. You've got the right,
是m和n的最大值？你说得也对
it's theta of the max. It's not the max.
它和最大值是同阶的  不过不是最大值
Max would be, in this case,
这最大值应该是
you're saying it has height seven.
照你说的应该是7
But, I think you can sort of see, for example,
不过这里差不多可以目测
along a path like this that, in fact, I've only,
从这条路径下来
after going three levels, reduced m plus n,
只经过了三层  减少了——m加n
good, very good, m plus n.
很好  不错  m加n
So, height here is m plus n.
这个高度是m加n
OK, and its binary.
它是二分的
So, the height: that implies the work is
所以它的高度说明运算量
exponential in m and n. All that work,
是m+n的指数阶
and are we any better off than the brute force algorithm?
和穷举法相比  这个算法要更好吗
Not really.
其实不然
And, our technical term for this is slow.
我们对它的评价就是——龟速
OK, and we like speed.
我们都爱速度
OK, we like fast.
我们都渴望奔驰的感觉
OK, but I'm sure that some of you have observed
不过我想你们肯定已经察觉到
something interesting about this tree.
这个树有些很奇妙的特性
Yeah, there's a lot of repeated work here.
是的  有很多运算是重复的
Right, there's a lot of repeated work.
是的  重复的运算有很多
In particular, this whole subtree,
尤其是这里  这里的整个子树
and this whole subtree, OK, they are the same.
还有这边的子树  它们是完全一样的
That's the same subtree,
它们都是一样的子树
the same subproblem that you are solving.
也就是你要解决的相同子问题
OK, you can even see over here,
这里也可以看到
there is even similarity between this whole subtree
这个地方的这个子树就等于
and this whole subtree.
这边这个子树
OK, so there's lots of repeated work.
所以说重复的运算有很多
OK, and one thing is, if you want to do things fast,
要注意  如果你想快速完成工作
don't keep doing the same thing.
那就不要做重复的工作
OK, don't keep doing the same thing.
好的  不要一直做重复的事情
When you find you are repeating something,
所以当你发现你在做重复的事
figure out a way of not doing it.
去找找能不再重复它的方法
So, that brings up our second hallmark for dynamic programming
于是  接下来动态规划的第二个特征就闪亮登场了
And that's a property called overlapping subproblems,
这个特征叫做重叠子问题
OK? OK, recursive solution contains
一个递归的过程包含
many, excuse me, contains a small number of
很多  抱歉  是少数
distinct subproblems repeated many times.
独立的子问题被反复计算了多次
And once again, this is important enough to put a box around
我又要把这个地方框起来了  因为的确很重要
I don't put boxes around too many things.
我不怎么喜欢框
Maybe I should put more boxes around things.
也许我应该多用框
This is definitely one to put a box around,
毫无疑问这里应该用框
OK? So, for example, so here we have a recursive solution.
比如说  这有一个递归
This tree is exponential in size.
这是个指数阶的树
It's two to the m plus n in height, in size,
高度是2^(m+n)
in the total number of problems
应该是总的问题数
I actually implemented like that.
我是想说的是这个意思
But how many distinct subproblems are there? m times n, OK?
那么有多少独立的子问题？ m乘n  对吧？
So, the longest common subsequence, the subproblem space
那么LCS问题的子问题空间
contains m times n, distinct subproblems.
包含了m乘n个独立的子问题
OK, and then this is a small number compared with
这个数字显得微不足道
two to the m plus n, or two to the n,
相比较于2^(m+n)或者2^n
or two to the m, or whatever.
或者2^m神马的
OK, this is small,
总之这个数很小
OK, because for each subproblem,
因为在每个子问题中
it's characterized by an i and a j.
这个数是由i和j来表示的
An i goes from one to m,
i是从1到m
and j goes from one to n, OK?
j从1到n
There aren't that many different subproblems.
实际的数字没有看起来那么多
It's just the product of the two.
只是它们俩的乘积
So, here's an improved algorithm,
这是一个改进版的算法
which is often a good way to solve it.
是个解决问题的好办法
It's an algorithm called a memo-ization algorithm.
这个算法叫做备忘法
And, this is memo-ization, not memorization because
注意  这是备忘法而不是记忆法
what you're going to do is make a little memo
你要做的就是在计算子问题的时候
whenever you solve a subproblem.
用备忘的方式记录一下
Make a little memo that says I solved this already.
做备忘的意思就是我已经算完了
And if ever you are asked for it rather than recalculating it
如果你需要这个值的时候 就不用重新算一次
say, oh, I see that.
你可以微微一笑
I did that before. Here's the answer,
然后说：我已经做过了  结果在这呢
OK? So, here's the code.
好的  这是它的代码
It's very similar to that code.
和那个代码很像
So, it basically keeps a table around of c[i,j].
其实就是把c[i,j]存成一个表
It says, what we do is we check.
我们要做的就是判断
If the entry for c[i,j] is nil,
如果c[i,j]是空的
we haven't computed it, then we compute it.
也就是说它还没被算过  于是我们把它算出来
And, how do we compute it?
然后呢  怎么算出来的？
Just the same way we did before.
就是我们做过的
OK, so this whole part here, OK,
所有的这部分
is exactly what we have had before.
就是我们做过的那些
It's the same as before.
完全相同
And then, we just return c[i,j].
然后  我们就返回c[i,j]
If we don't bother to keep recalculating,
这时我们不用管重复计算的事了
OK, so if it's nil, we calculate it.
如果是空的  那么我们就进行计算
Otherwise, we just return it.
否则  返回它就行了
It's not calculated, calculate and return it.
没算过  就去算
Otherwise, just return it
算过了  就返回
OK, pretty straightforward code.
相当明了的代码
Ok.
好的
OK, now the tricky thing is how much time
有意思的问题是 我们要花多长时间
does it take to execute this?
来执行它
This takes a little bit of thinking.
需要开动一下脑筋
Yeah? Yeah, it takes order MN.
嗯？是的  花费是O(mn)
OK, why is that?
这是为什么？
Yeah, but I have to look up c[i,j].
是的  我得调用c[i,j]
I might call c[i,j] a bunch of times.
我可能会调用c[i,j]好多次
When I'm doing this,
这样做的话
I'm still calling it recursively.
我还是在递归地调用它
Yeah, so you have to, so each recursive call
所以你不得不这样  每个递归调用
is going to look at, and the worst-case, say,
都按最坏情况算的话
is going to look at the max of these two things.
就是找这两个的最大值
Well, this is going to involve
这就包括了
a recursive call, and a lookup.
一次递归调用  一次查找
So, this might take a fair amount of effort to calculate.
计算这个要花费相当大的代价
I mean, you're right, and your intuition is right.
你说得对  直觉很对
Let's see if we can get a more precise argument,
我们来看看如何得到更精确的证明
why this is taking order m times n.
为什么这个花费O(mn)
What's going on here?
这是在做什么？
Because not every time I call
并不是说每次的调用
this is it going to just take me
花费的时间
a constant amount of work to do this.
都是一个常数
Sometimes it's going to take me a lot of work.
有时候计算量很繁重
Sometimes I get lucky, and I return it.
有时我人品爆发  直接就能返回它了
So, your intuition is dead on.
所以你的直觉是很准确的
It's dead on. We just need a little bit more
相当准确  我们需要的只是一些
articulate explanation, so that everybody is on board.
更清晰有力的论述 来让大家信服
Try again? Good, at most three times, yeah.
还想试试？对了  最多是三次  没错
OK, so that's one way to look at it. Yeah.
这么想的确说得通
There is another way to look at it that's kind of
你也可以这么想  它是一种
what you are expressing there is an amortized,
按你的说法是平摊的方式
a bookkeeping, way of looking at this.
记账方法  来看这个问题
What's the amortized cost?
平摊代价是多少？
You could say what the amortized cost of calculating
比如说这几个调用
one of these, where basically whenever I call it
当它们中的某一个
I'm going to charge a constant amount for looking up.
我想让每一次的调用 都花费同样运算量
And so, I could get to look up whatever is in here
这样我要找这里的结果时
to call the things.
只要调用就好了
But if it, in fact, so in some sense, this charge here,
某种意义上来说  这几条语句是调用的花费
of calling it and returning it, etc
我向它们收取调用和返回的费用
OK, so I charged these lines and this line to the caller.
这几行还有这一行是调用花费
And I charge the rest of these lines to the c[i,j] element.
然后中间这几行是c[i,j]的花费
And then, the point is that every caller basically only
要注意的是 基本上每一次的调用
ends up being charged for a constant amount of stuff.
其花费都是常数量的
OK, to calculate one c[i,j],it's only an amortized
所以计算一个c[i,j]  平摊起来
constant amount of stuff that I'm charging to that
我也只需要常数量的运算
calculation of i and j, that calculation of i and j.
我对一个c[i,j]的花费就这么多
OK, so you can view it in terms of
你可以把它看成
amortized analysis doing a bookkeeping argument that just says,
用记账方法来进行平摊分析
let me charge enough to calculate my own,
每个计算单元 我都收够一定的费用
do all my own local things plus enough to
来支付这一步的操作 再加上
look up the value in the next level and get it returned.
支付查看下一层元素和返回的操作
OK, and then if it has to go off and calculate,
即使它真的要继续往下运算
well, that's OK because that's all been
那也无所谓  因为这些花费
charged to a different ij at that point.
会由另外的ij来负责
So, every cell only costs me a constant amount of time
所以  每个计算单元都只花费常数量的时间
that order MN cells total of order constant work per entry.
在O(mn)中  每次都花费常数量的计算
OK, and you can sort of use
你可以用
an amortized analysis to argue that.
平摊分析来证明它
How much space does it take?
它的空间花费是多少？
We haven't usually looked at space,
我们一般不关注空间
but here we are going to start looking at space.
但这里我们得开始看看空间的问题了
That turns out, for some of these algorithms,
对于一些算法来说
to be really important.
空间是很重要的
How much space do I need, storage space?
我需要多少空间？储存空间？
Yeah, also m times n, OK, to store the c[i,j] table.
是的  也是m乘n  就是储存c[i,j]的表
OK, the rest, storing x and y,
剩下的用来储存x和y的
OK, that's just m plus n.
只有m+n那么多
So, that's negligible,
可以忽略不计了
but mostly I need the space m times n.
我需要的空间大概就是m乘n那么多
So, this memo-ization type algorithm is a really good
所以备忘法的算法
strategy in programming for many things where,
在编程中是很有用的策略
when you have the same parameters,
当你有相同传入的参数
you're going to get the same results.
你就会得到相同的结果
It doesn't work in programs where you have
当然它也有不管用的时候
a side effect, necessarily, that is,
那就是当你的运算
when the calculation for a given set of parameters
有很多传入参数
might be different on each call.
都是不一样的时候
But for something which isessentially like a
不过对于这种
functional programming type of environment,
函数式的编程
then if you've calculated it once, you can look it up.
如果你已经计算过一组参数的结果  那直接查找就好了
And, so this is very helpful.
总之这东西好处多多
But, it takes a fair amount of space,
然而  它也花费了相当多的空间
and it also doesn't proceed in a very orderly way.
而且在空间上也不是很整齐的
So, there is another strategy for doing
所以有另一种策略来解决重复运算
exactly the same calculation in a bottom-up way.
就是用自底向上的方法
And that's what we call dynamic programming.
这才是传说中的的真·动态规划
OK, the idea is to compute the table bottom-up.
主要思想就是自底向上地计算表格
I think I'm going to get rid of,
把这边擦掉
I think what we'll do is we'll just use,
就用这边的这块吧
actually I think what I'm going to do is use this board.
啊  我还是用后面这块吧
OK, so here's the idea.
我们要做的是
What we're going to do is look at the c[i,j] table and
我们要做的就是观察c[i,j]表格
realize that there's actually an orderly
然后意识到其实可以按照一定顺序
way of filling in the table.
来填这个表
This is sort of a top-down with memo-ization.
前面讲的是自顶向下的备忘法
OK, but there's actually a way
不过实际上还有一种方式
we can do it bottom up.
我们可以自底向上地来做
So, here's the idea.
我们来看一下
So, let's make our table.
这是我们的表格
OK, so there's x.
这是x
And then, there's y.
这是y
And, I'm going to initialize the empty string.
我需要先对这些空项进行初始化
I didn't cover the base cases for c[i,j],
我没有覆盖掉c[i,j]的初始值
but c of zero meaning a prefix with no elements in it.
c[0]的含义就是一个没有任何元素的前缀
The prefix of that without anything else, the length is zero.
这个前缀里面什么都没有  它的长度也就是0
OK, so that's basically how I'm going to bound the borders here.
画出这些只是要划定一个边界
And now, what I can do is just use my formula,
现在  我要做的就是套公式了
which I've conveniently erased up there, OK,
公式已经被我擦得灰飞烟灭了  好吧
to compute what is the longest common subsequence,
为了计算LCS
length of the longest common subsequence
计算LCS的长度
from this character in y,
从y里的这个字符开始
and this character in x up to this character.
还有x里的这个字符
So here, for example, they don't match.
比如说这里  它们不相等
So, it's the maximum of these two values.
于是它等于这两个的最大值
Here, they do match.
这里它们相等了
OK, so it says it's one plus the value here.
它就等于1加上左上方这个数
And, I'm going to draw a line.
我来画条连线
Whenever I'm going to get a match,
每次我找到了一个相等的字符
I'm going to draw a line like that,
我就这么画条连线
indicating that I had that first case,
意思是我第一次遇到了
the case where they had a good match.
它们相等的情况
And so, all I'm doing is applying that recursive formula
然后我要做的就是应用那个递归公式
from the theorem that we proved.
就是我们证明过的定理里的那个
So here, it's basically they don't match.
这里它们不相等
So, it's the maximum of those two.
所以是两个的最大值
Here, they match.
这里相等了
So, it's one plus that guy. Here, they don't match.
所以是1加上这货  这里不相等
So, it's basically the maximum of these two.
就是那两个的最大值
Here, they don't match. So it's the maximum.
这里不相等  取最大值
So, it's one plus that guy.
这里是1加前面的
So, everybody understand how I filled out that first row?
大家都明白第一行是怎么填出来的了吧？
OK, well that you guys can help.
很好  这样你们就可以派上用场了
OK, so this one is what?
它等于多少？
Just call it out. Zero, good.
说出来就行  0  很好
One, because it's the maximum, one, two, right.
1  因为是取最大值  1,2  没错
This one, now, gets from there,
这个呢  然后这个
two, two. OK, here, zero,
2,2  好的  这里  0
one, because it's the maximum of those two.
1  因为是取最大值
Two, two, two, good.
2,2,2  很好
One, one, two, two, two, three,
1,1,2,2,2,3
three. One, two, three,
3,1,2,3
get that line, three, four,
继续 3,4
OK. One there, three,
1,3
three, four, good, four.
3,4  很好  4
OK, and our answer: four.
好的  于是我们的答案就是：4
So this is blindingly fast code if you code this up,
显而易见  这是很快的代码
OK, because it gets to use the fact that modern machines in
因为这用到了现代机器的一个性质
particular do very well on regular strides through memory.
如果对内存的操作是有规律性的  那它们通常很给力
So, if you're just plowing through memory across like this,
如果你按这个顺序使用内存
OK, and your two-dimensional array is stored in that order,
这个二维数组就是按这种顺序存下来
which it is, otherwise you go this way,
否则的话就是按这种顺序
stored in that order.
按这种顺序存储的
This can really fly in terms of the speed of the calculation.
这个算法跑起来就是飞一样的感觉
So, how much time did it take us to do this?
那么  我们花了多少时间来干这个？
Yeah, order MN, theta MN. Yeah?
是的O(mn)  Θ(mn)  是吧？
We'll talk about space in just a minute.
我们稍后就讲空间的问题
OK, so hold that question. Good question,
所以hold住你的问题  那是个好问题
good question, already, wow,
很好的问题
good, OK, how do I now figure out, remember,
很好  那么我们是怎么算出——记得吗
we had the simplification.
我们有简化的方法
We were going to just calculate the length.
我们只需计算出长度
OK, it turns out I can now figure out a
然后我就可以找出
particular sequence that matches it.
一个那么长的序列来
And basically, I do that.
我要做的是
I can reconstruct the longest common subsequence
通过回溯法重建LCS
So essentially I start here.
所以我从这里出发
Here I have a choice because this one was dependent on,
这里我做了一次选择
since it doesn't have a bar here,
因为这里没有连线
it was dependent on one of these two.
它取决于这两个值其中的一个
So, let me go this way.
所以来向这边走
OK, and now I have a diagonal element here.
现在这里出现了一条斜线
So what I'll do is simply mark the character that
所以我们要做的就是标记
appeared in those positions as I go this way.
出现在这些位置上的字符
I have three here.
这里是3
And now, let me keep going, three here,
然后继续走  这是3
and now I have another one.
这里又发现了一条斜线
So that means this character gets selected.
意思是这个字符被选上了
And then I go up to here, OK, and then up to here.
往上走到这  然后到这
And now I go diagonally again,
然后再往斜上走
which means that this character is selected.
也就是说这个字符也被选上了
And I go to here, and then I go here.
然后这边  这边
And then, I go up here and this character is selected.
然后继续向上  这两个字符被选上了
So here is my longest common subsequence.
于是这就是我的LCS
And this was just one path back.
当然这只是一种路径
I could have gone a path like this and
我也可以不走寻常路
gotten a different longest common subsequence.
得到一个截然不同的LCS
OK, so that simplification of just saying, look,
这种简化其实就是在说  看吧
let me just run backwards and figure it out,
我只是往回走了几步就能找出LCS
that's actually pretty good because it means
这是相当不错的  因为这意味着
that by just calculating the value,
在计算的过程中
then figuring out these back pointers to
用这些反向指针
let me reconstruct it is a fairly simple process.
来重建LCS其实是很容易的
OK, if I had to think about that to begin with,
如果我想从前向后建立LCS
it would have been a much bigger mess.
那将会困难重重
OK, so the space, I just mentioned,
那么接着我刚才说的  空间问题
was order MN because we still need the table.
是O(mn)因为我们还是要用到这个表格
So, you can actually do the min of m and n.
其实用O(min(m,n))的空间就能解决问题
OK, to get to your question,
为了回答你的问题
how do you do the min of m and n?
怎么做O(min(m,n))的空间？
Diagonal stripes won't give you min of m and n.
按对角线不会得到min(m,n)
That'll give you the sum of m and n.
那会得到m,n的和
So, going in stripes,
按对角线走
maybe I'm not quite sure I know what you mean.
也许我没理解你的话
So, you're saying, so what's the order I would do here?
好的  按你说的  我按什么顺序处理这个地方？
So, I would start.
好的  我开始了
I would do this one first. Then which one would I do?
我从这里开始  下一个是哪个？
This one and this one?
这个？
And then, this one,this one, this one, like this?
这里  再到这里.....像这样？
That's a perfectly good order.
这的确是很好的顺序
OK, and so you're saying, then,
你的意思是
so I'm keeping the diagonal there all the time.
每次都保存对角线上的元素
So, you're saying the length of the diagonal
也就是说对角线的长度
is the min of m and n?
就是min(m,n)？
I think that's right.
嗯  的确是这样
OK, there is another way you can do it
你还可以用一种方法
that's a little bit more straightforward,
这种方法更直观
which is you compare m to n.
你只要比较m和n
Whichever is smaller, well, first of all,
看看那个更小  那么首先
let's just do this existing algorithm.
我们就从这个算法入手
If I just simply did row by row,
如果我按行来做
I don't need more than a previous row.
我不需要前一行的数据
OK, I just need one row at a time.
每次只需要一行就够了
So, I can go ahead and compute just one row
我可以只用一行计算
because once I computed the succeeding row,
因为一旦我算除了后面的行
the first row is unimportant.
第一行就无关紧要了
And in fact, I don't even need the whole row.
其实我都不需要这整个行
All I need is just the current row that I'm on,
我需要的只有现在我用的这一行
plus one or two elements of the previous row,
和上一行的一两个元素
plus the end of the previous row.
还有上一行的末尾
So, I use a prefix of this row, and an extra two elements,
所以我用到了这一行的前缀  还有上一行两个元素
So, it's actually, you can do it with one row,
实际上  你需要的只有一行
plus order one element.
加上O(1)这么多的元素
And then, I could do it either running vertically or running
我可以选择是横向还是纵向
horizontally, whichever one gives me the smaller space.
哪样省空间我就选哪样
OK, and it might be that your
可能你的那个
diagonal trick would work there too.
对角线法也能行
I'd have to think about that. Yeah?
我得想一想
Ooh, that's a good question.
喔  问得好
So, you can do the calculation of the length,
现在可以做到的是计算LCS长度
and run row plus order one elements.
并且只需要一行加上O(1)的空间
OK, and our exercise, and this is a hard exercise,
那么我们的作业就是  这是个高难度的作业
OK, so that a good one to do is to do small space
就是用很小的空间
and allow you to reconstruct the LCS because
就重建出LCS
the naive way that we were just doing it,
就用我们刚才很天真的算法
it's not clear how you would go backwards from that
其实如何进行回溯有些复杂
because you've lost the information.
因为你丢失了很多信息
OK, so this is actually a very interesting and tricky problem.
所以说这是一个相当开动脑筋的问题
And, it turns out it succumbs of all things to divide and conquer,
它遵循分而治之的方法
OK, rather than some more straightforward tabular thing.
而不是一些简单的制表之类的东西
so very good practice, for example,
用来练手很不错  比如
for the upcoming take home quiz,
让它出现在下一次课后作业里
OK, which is all design and cleverness type quiz.
都是很精巧很锻炼思维的问题
OK, so this is a good one for people to take on.
做做很有好处
So, this is basically the tabular method
这就是备忘法
that's called dynamic programming.
那个叫动态规划
OK, memo-ization is not dynamic programming,
备忘法和动态规划是两个东西
even though it's related. It's memo-ization.
即使它们之间有关系
And, we're going to see a whole bunch of other problems that
我们还将看到很多其它的问题
succumb to dynamic programming approaches.
都遵从动态规划的方式
It's a very cool method, and on the homework,
这是很牛的方法  在你们的作业里
so let me just mention the homework again.
我再提一次作业的事
On the homework, we're going to look at a
作业里面  你们会看到一个问题
problem called the edit distance problem.
叫做编辑距离问题
Edit distance is you are given two strings.
编辑距离问题是给定你两个字符串
And you can imagine that you're typing in
然后你可以脑补一下
a keyboard with one of the strings there.
你用一个上面只有一串字母的键盘打字
And what you have to do is by doing inserts, and deletes,
你所能做的就是插入  删除
and replaces, and moving the cursor around,
替换  还得移动光标
you've got to transform one string to the next.
你要把这个字符串变形成另一个
And, each of those operations has a cost.
每次这种操作都有代价
And your job is to minimize the cost of
你的任务就是
transforming the one string into the other.
将这种变形的计算量减到最小
This actually turns out also to
这个问题
be useful for computational biology applications.
在生物学上也是很常见的
And, in fact, there have been editors,
而且  还有各种编辑器也会用到它
screen editors, text editors,
像影片编辑器  文本编辑器
that implement algorithms of this nature in order to minimize
都要用这样的算法来使
the number of characters that have to be sent
发送到系统的I/O数据最小化
So, the warning is, you better get going on your programming
提醒你们一下  你们最好
on problem one on the homework today
今天就开始做作业一
if at all possible because whenever I assign programming,
因为我分配任务的时候
since we don't do that as sort of a routine thing,
并不是按步骤一点点来的
I'm just concerned for some people that there will not
我只担心有些同学可能
be able to get things like the input and output to work,
不能及时得到作业所需要的输入输出神马的
We have example problems, and such, on the website.
在网站上有一些示例问题
And we also have, you can write it in any language you want,
你可以用任何你想用的语言写
including Matlab,
包括 Matlab
Python, whatever your favorite,
Python  只要是你喜欢的
the solutions will be written in Java and Python.
答案会用Java和Python写出
OK, so the fastest solutions are likely to be written in c.
用c语言写出来的应该是最快的
OK, you can also do it in assembly language if you care to.
你也可以用汇编来写
You laugh. I used to be in assembly
你们还是太年轻了 大叔我当年用的就是汇编
language programmer back in the days of yore.
在我那激情燃烧的岁月
OK, so I do encourage people to get started on this because let
我建议你们马上就开始做这个
me mention, the other thing is that this particular problem on
我提一句  另一件事就是这个习题集里
this problem set is an absolutely mandatory problem.
这些题是必做题
OK, all the problems are mandatory,
都是必做的题
but as you know you can skip them and it doesn't
不过你也知道你可以跳着做
hurt you too much if you only skip one or two.
适当的跳几道题不会有大问题
This one, you skip, hurts big time: one letter grade.
不过这一个  你要是跳了  那就给跪吧 成绩立马降一级
It must be done.
都给我乖乖做好
OK, and charge twice as much for each insert.
然后 对每个插入都收取两倍的代价